<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Webgl | Carlos A. Lugo's site]]></title>
  <link href="http://calugo.github.io/blog/categories/webgl/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://calugo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-19T01:22:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://calugo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carlos A Lugo Vélez]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evolution and Genotype-Phenotype Mappings (RNA Networks)]]></title>
    <link href="http://calugo.github.io/blog/2014/10/14/evolution-and-genotype-phenotype-mappings/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T16:59:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://calugo.github.io/blog/2014/10/14/evolution-and-genotype-phenotype-mappings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="if-you-want-to-understand-function-study-structure---more---">If you want to understand function, study structure.<!-- more --></h2>

<p align="justify">
The above statement is attributed to F. H. C. Crick and its the opening quote of the excellent
 book on networks
<a href="http://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199591756.001.0001/acprof-9780199591756">The Structure of Complex Networks</a>
 by E. Estrada. The mathematical theory of evolution as the result of motions in the space of sequences or <b>genotypes</b> is
 and active field of research which involves the use of tools and techniques ranging from the theory of stochastic processes
  to bioinformatics passing through the full family of  <b>&#8216;omics&#8217;</b>.
</p>

<p align="justify">The project I am involved at the minute, is the one of studying the topologies spanned by
the sets of all the possible <b>genotypes</b> or sequences of a given length $l$ which can be form using the four letter
 alphabet $\{A,C,T,G\}$
and calculating their corresponding biochemical function or <b>phenotype</b>. Redundancy will divide the full space of $4^{l}$ into $N$ subsets
$\{\Omega_k\}_{k=1}^N$ each one representing a phenotype. Then, by employing the metric induced by single point mutations the sets $\Omega_k$ can be
<b>connected</b> if they posses sequences which are away from each other a <d>distance</d> $d_h=1$.  
</p>
<p align="justify">
The knowledge of the resultant graph or <b>phenotype landscape</b> allow us to treat the problem of evolution as the problem of
 a walker in a complex network and which can be treated  
 by using the standard tools of statistical physics. This approach relies on a very strong assumption. Namely, the knowledge of
a well defined <b>genotype-phenotype mapping</b>, this is not easy to satisfy for the vast majority of real systems, however for the case of RNA molecules and moderately
 long sequences, the secondary structure can be considered as a very good approximation or proxy for such mapping.
</p>

<p align="justify">
This project is very much work in progress, but because I like to share code and data, I prepared
an Ipython notebook which illustrates the ideas of the previous paragraph (construction the phenotype landscape)
for a very special system: <b>the genetic code</b>. For the case of RNA a nice example is for instance the banner at
 the main page of this site.
</p>

<p align="justify">
In the notebook, it is shown how to generate all the codons, organise them into
 their respective aminoacid class, and how to construct and draw a number neutral networks
diagrams like the one shown below. The entire topology is generated by linking every pair of codons
one mutation away.
</p>

<p>
<a target="_blank" href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/github/calugo/RNA-NETS/blob/master/NOTEBOOKS/AMINOACIDS.ipynb">
Genetic code&#8217;s notebook and neutral networks (nbviewer)</a>
</p>

<p align="justify">
As stated before the notebook contains code to generate networks like the one below. The image is also a link to the source
code (Github repo).
</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/calugo/RNA-NETS"><img src="/images/amino2.png" width="700" target="_blank" /></a>
</div>

<h2 id="webgl-interactive-explorer">WebGL interactive explorer</h2>

<p align="justify">
 The repository also contains the the code of a very robust, but still in a very early stage of development, interactive
 network explorer for the same system. The aim of that visualization tool is non other but to
 been able to quickly render and explore networks and multiplexes with interactive features in real time
 within the browser, applying a precalculated layout (Notice the similarities between the two dimensional and three dimensional
   representations).
 </p>
<p align="justify">
 The latter is also an active project and it is updated often, so make sure check the site
 every now and then to see if there are any improvements.  If there is enough interest
  we  will set up a curated repository. For now its just a lunch time hack
 of the <b>draggable nodes</b> example at <a href="http://threejs.org">three.js</a>
</p>

<p>
Be sure that your browser supports WebGL and that it is enabled (help <a href="http://get.webgl.org/">here</a>).</p>

<p>

 <a target="_blank" href="/jsnet/index.html"><b>THREE.JS-WEBGL INTERACTIVE GENETIC CODE NETWORK EXPLORER HERE</b></a>.  
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
